I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we examine the best
way to have the most regular
and otherwise agreeable
bowel movements.
And we’re going to start with
the best pooping position.
While squatting continues
to be the traditional position
in populations of Asia and Africa,
Westerners have become
accustomed to sitting on toilet
seats. And when we do that,
when we sit upright,
our poop is forced to make
a nearly 90-degree turn,
the so-called recto-anal angle.
Now, that's a good
thing in terms of
keeping us from pooping our
pants every time we sit down.
But when it comes to doing our
business, the sitting toilet posture
defeats the purpose of our
body's brilliant design—
like trying to drive a car without
releasing the parking brake.
Yet many physicians
are hesitant to discuss
such an unmentionable bodily
function or may just be ignorant.
Doctors don't know squat.
Of course, this is coming from
someone who owns a company
selling people squatting
platforms for their toilets.
In a previous video, I talked about
those little footstools you can use
to raise your knees when you
assume the pooping position,
but they were not found to
make a difference in terms
of self-described
difficulty in defecating
or the average time spent
emptying one's bowels.
But those stools give only
a measly 4-inch boost.
The so-called Squatty Potty
is twice that height,
and while you have to
admire their graphics,
from booty blockage to fecal fiesta,
complete with little rainbow poops,
it had never been put
to the test until now.
The Implementation of
a Defecation Posture
Modification Device, i.e.,
Squatty Potty, and it worked!
Increased feelings of bowel
emptiness, reduced straining,
and about a minute off of
their on-the-pot reading time.
The only downside
is the discomfort.
Even just a 6-inch riser was found
to cause such extreme discomfort
in research subjects
in a previous trial,
they'd abandoned even
trying to study it.
How else could we get that
same change in angle you get
from raising your feet?
How about just tipping forward?
Look familiar? It's like that famous
sculpture by Rodin, The Thinker.
And indeed, Cleveland Clinic
researchers set out to study
"The Thinker" position for
defecation, and were able to show
an opening of the ano-rectal
angle, as measured using
cinedefecography—your
S.A.T. word for the day,
meaning basically
x-ray poop movie—
opening to more than 130
degrees, better than what
you can get just raising your feet,
which is only around 90 degrees.
So "The Thinker" position may be a
more efficient method for defecation.
and may help with constipation,
but it has not yet been
formally put to the test.
As an aside, you can imagine
how the worst position might be
flat on your back using a bedpan,
because the spike in blood pressure
in your heart and brain when
you bear down, straining at stool,
is associated with sudden death
from heart attack and stroke.
In fact, it's been found to be the
most common activity of daily living
being performed at the
time of death in Japan.
And those who can't get out of bed
would seem to be especially at risk.
That's why, if at all possible,
it can help to sit people up in bed
to cause less strain on the system.
It's important to take a step back,
though, in this sitting vs. squatting
debate as this commentary
did nearly 50 years ago.
Yes, the squatting position is
said to be natural, since it's used
by so-called primitive peoples
who pass large stools easily,
such that squatting advocates
blame the porcelain throne
on all manner of Western maladies.
But does the position
really make a difference
if you're eating the right foods?
The man who squats because he
has no modern plumbing also tends
to eat more natural foods that
haven't had the fiber processed out.
Adding fiber to the diet can enable
constipated patients to poop
effortlessly without having to squat
over some hole in the ground.
So maybe if we just change
the design of our diets,
we don't have to change
the design of our plumbing.
In our next story, we
look at how most people
have between 3 bowel
movements a day
and 3 a week!
But normal doesn’t
necessarily mean optimal.
Ancient Egypt was one
of the great civilizations,
lasting for 3,000 years,
its knowledge of medicine
vastly underestimated.
They had medical sub-specialties.
The pharaohs, for
example, had access
to dedicated physicians
to be guardians
of the royal bowel movement,
a title alternately translated
from the hieroglyphics to
mean Shepherd of the Anus.
How's that for a resume builder?
Today, the primacy of
its importance continues,
with some calling for bowel
habits to be considered
a vital sign on how
the body is functioning,
along with blood pressure,
heart, breathing rate.
Although we may not particularly
like hearing the details
of someone else's
bowel movement,
it is a function that nurses
and doctors need to assess.
Surprisingly, the colon remained
relatively unexplored territory,
one of the body's final frontiers.
For example, current concepts
of what "normal" stools are like
primarily emanates from
the detailed records
of 12 consecutive bowel
movements in 27 healthy subjects
from the United Kingdom who boldly
went where no one had gone before.
Those must have been
really detailed records.
The reason we need
to define normal,
when it comes to bowel movement
frequency, for example,
is how else can you define concepts
like constipation or diarrhea
if you don't know what normal is.
Standard physiology textbooks
may not be helpful in this regard
implying that anything
from one bowel movement
every few weeks or months to
24 a day can be regarded as normal.
Once every few months?
Of all human bodily
functions defecation
is perhaps the least
understood and least studied.
Can't you just ask people? Turns
out people tend to exaggerate.
There's a discrepancy between
what people report
and what researchers find when
they actually have them recorded.
It wasn't until 2010 when
we got the first serious look,
defining normal stool
frequency as between
three per week and three per day,
based on the fact that that's where
98% of people tended to fall. But normal
doesn't necessarily mean optimal.
Having a "normal" salt intake can
lead to a "normal" blood pressure,
which can help us to die
from all the "normal" causes,
like heart attacks and strokes.
Having a normal cholesterol level
in a society where it's normal
to drop dead of heart disease --
our number one killer --
not necessarily a good thing.
And indeed significant
proportions of people
with "normal bowel function"
reported urgency, straining,
incomplete defecation,
leading the researchers
to conclude that
that kind of thing must
just be normal.
Normal, maybe, if you're
eating a fiber deficient diet.
But not normal for our species.
Defecation should not
be a painful exercise.
This is readily demonstrable.
For example, the majority of rural
Africans eating their traditional
fiber-rich plant-based diets
can usually pass without straining
a stool specimen on demand.
See, the rectum may
need to accumulate
4 or 5 ounces of fecal matter before
the defecation reflex is fully initiated,
and so if you don't even build up that
much over the day you'd have to strain
to prime the rectal pump.
Hippocrates thought
bowel movements
should ideally be two
or three times a day,
which is what you
see in populations
on traditional plant-based diets,
on the kind of fiber intakes
you see in our fellow great apes, and
what may be more representative
of the types of diets we evolved
eating for millions of years.
It seems somewhat
optimistic, though,
to expect the average American
to adopt a rural African diet.
We can, however, eat more
plant-based and bulk up enough
to take the Hippocratic oath
to go 2 to 3 times a day.
No need to obsess about it.
In fact there's actually a Bowel
Obsession Syndrome
characterized in part by ideational
rambling over bowel habits,
but three times a day makes sense.
We have what's called
a gastrocolic reflex,
which consists of a prompt activation
of muscular waves in our colon
within 1 to 3 minutes of the ingestion
of the first mouthfuls of food.
Even just talking about food can cause
your brain to increase colon activity.
This suggests the body figured
that one meal should be just enough
to fill you up down there.
So maybe we should eat
enough unprocessed plant foods
to get up to three a day, a
movement for every meal.
In our final story today,
prunes, figs, and exercise
are put to the test as natural
home remedies for constipation.
The act of defecation involves
a very private sphere
and is the object of cultural
taboos, so much so that
it’s rarely thought of, even by
physicians—but it should be.
Constipation accounts for three
million annual visits to doctors
in the United States and
800,000 emergency room visits.
Depending on how you define
it, up to 80 percent
of the population may be suffering.
Even people who don’t
think they’re constipated
may very well be
clinically constipated.
A quarter of their so-
called healthy subjects
reported experiencing
incomplete emptying,
and approximately half
indicated increased straining.
In fact, more than
half had found blood
on their toilet paper
within the past year.
In severe cases, the blood
pressure spike associated with
straining at stool can even
trigger a heart attack or a stroke.
There are drugs for it.
There are always drugs,
resulting in side effects
like headache, nausea, diarrhea,
and abdominal pain, leaving
most patients unsatisfied.
So why not instead just
try to treat the cause?
Common causes of chronic
constipation include lack of
adequate whole plant foods
or insufficient water intake,
and so making changes in the
patient’s diet and lifestyle
is the preferred method for
relieving constipation.
Such nonpharmacological clinical
effective interventions
including engaging in physical
activity for about 30 minutes a day.
A systematic review and meta-
analysis found aerobic exercise
interventions help, starting
at about 140 minutes a week.
And then, of course, a diet
centered around whole plant foods,
which are the only naturally
concentrated sources of fiber.
Any plants in particular?
If you give elderly women
with severe constipation about
a dozen prunes a day they
experience significant
improvement within the first week.
The control group in the study
wasn’t told to do anything though.
And any time you have one
group doing something and
the other doing nothing, you can’t
discount the placebo effect.
And the placebo response for
constipation trials can range
up to 44 percent, meaning up to
nearly half of the people given
a sugar pill claimed to
experience an improvement.
So, that’s why we need
studies like this.
Subjects were randomized
to about 8 prunes a day
plus a large glass of water;
12 prunes and water;
or just the water alone; so,
even the control group got
an intervention they were told
might help with constipation.
Previous studies mostly
assigned 10 prunes or so a day,
so the researchers wanted to
see if more was better or less
was sufficient and...they found
a significant improvement
in stool bulk on the prunes
and a significant increase
in bowel movement frequency,
though no real difference
between 8 and 12; so,
8 a day seems sufficient.
Prunes even appear superior
to psyllium, sold as Metamucil,
beating it out in terms of improved
stool frequency and consistency.
We used to think it was
just all the fiber in prunes
that was helping, but prune
juice evidently works too,
which, like most juices,
has had the fiber removed.
Other potential active components
include a natural sugar alcohol
known as sorbitol that’s
used in some sugar-free gum.
Once you eat more than a dozen
or so large prunes a day, however,
the dose of sorbitol could
start reaching laxative levels
in susceptible individuals.
So, be careful.
If you don’t have constipation,
should you avoid prunes?
That’s been put to the test, and...
most people should
be able to eat a dozen or
so a day without any issues.
In fact, it’s interesting to
note that prunes have been
traditionally used as both a
laxative and an antidiarrheal remedy.
What about dried figs? One
of the few medicinal plants
mentioned explicitly in the Bible.
Researchers took patients with the
type of irritable bowel syndrome
characterized by constipation
and randomized them to one fig
with breakfast and one fig with
lunch, each with a glass of water,
and there was a significant improvement
in frequency of defecation
and a significant drop in
the frequency of hard stools,
compared to control. Ah, but
what was the control?
The control group was just asked
to continue their normal diet.
In other words, to
do nothing special.
The placebo response for
irritable bowel is infamous.
Give people with IBS a fake sugar
pill, and sometimes 72 percent
say they magically feel better.
That’s why we need
this kind of study:
a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial.
Researchers made a gross-
sounding fig paste placebo
that supposedly had
the same taste, smell,
and appearance as the real deal.
Those who got the real
figs, about six a day,
seemed to improve colon transit
time, stool consistency,
and abdominal discomfort
compared to the placebo.
Researchers measured transit
time by having people swallow
little beads that would show up
on x-rays so they could track
the progress thorough
their digestive system.
They found that those eating
the real figs sped up their
gut movement by a full 24 hours
Defecation frequency per week
didn’t beat out placebo though,
and in fact, they tested
so many different outcomes
even the stool consistency
and tummy discomfort results
may have been statistical flukes.
So, it looks like prunes would
be the better treatment choice.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.